<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Inqury @ UC Santa Cruz</title>
    <description>UC Santa Cruz Research Magazine</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2015 15:59:00 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2015 15:59:00 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Single Cell Technology</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A new nanobiopsy technique helps scientists peer into cells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a tip so tiny it can’t be seen with a microscope, a pipette engineered by UC Santa Cruz researchers is small enough to pierce a single living cell without causing any damage. The computer-automated technique, developed
in Nader Pourmand’s multidisciplinary laboratory, Biosensors and Bioelectronics, was described in &lt;em&gt;ACS Nano&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We can now go in and sip a little content from acelltoseewhatitis doing, while it is doing it,” said Pourmand, professor of biomolecular engineering in the UC Santa Cruz Baskin School of Engineering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This nanopipetting method makes it possible for researchers to regularly monitor individual cells. Measuring minuscule changes in cell contents, such as sugar levels, can mark a cell’s metabolic march from healthy to abnormal. The scientists also showed they can extract single organelles and measure RNa or DNa samples to discover which genes are being turned on or off at any given time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Until now we’ve been looking at endpoints of disease, but there’s a lot we’re missing in between,” Pourmand said. “This technique can help us get those details.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this work, Pourmand’s team became a finalist in “Follow That Cell,” a national NIH competition for novel solutions to study single cell dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>/2015/single-cell-technology/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2015/single-cell-technology/</guid>
        
        
        <category>biomolecular engineering</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Sea Star Scourge</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;For the past two years, sea stars along the Pacific coast have suffered catastrophic die-offs. The disappearance of these key predators could have profound effects on their tide pool and near-shore ecosystems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In collaboration with UC Santa Cruz and other institutions, biologists at Cornell University identified a “sea star associated densovirus” as the most likely cause. Although the densovirus was a novel discovery for researchers, the infectious agent was found in museum specimens of sea stars collected in 1942. The study was published in the Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The question is why a virus that’s been around for years went rogue, or whether environmental stressors made the sea stars more susceptible,” said Peter Raimondi, UCSC professor and chair of ecology and evolutionary biology.
There may be good news, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In the last six months, we’re seeing more sea star babies than we’ve seen in some places for the last 15 years,” said Raimondi, who leads the Pacific Rocky Intertidal Monitoring Program. “If the disease is gone, this new generation could replenish populations more quickly than expected.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marm Kilpatrick, associate professor of ecology and evolutionary biology, and Melissa Miner, a research specialist at Long Marine Laboratory, also contributed to this study.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>/2015/sea-star-scourge/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2015/sea-star-scourge/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Sea Otter Supermoms</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Once hunted to near extinction, sea otters on California’s Central Coast have made a comeback. But a stall in population recovery, with higher than expected deaths among female sea otters, prompted UC Santa Cruz  marine biologist Nicole Thometz to investigate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thometz discovered the high-energy needs of pups may push their moms beyond their metabolic means. Her findings on “end lactation syndrome” were published in the Journal of Experimental Biology. The study was co-authored by Terrie Williams, professor of ecology and evolutionary biology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just to survive in a cold water habitat, these small marine mammals need to eat 25 percent of their body weight in food every day. “But we didn’t know how much more energy a mom needed to provide for her pup,” Thometz said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To calculate the daily caloric needs of pups, from birth until six months of age, Thometz observed 26 wild sea otters to construct their daily activity budgets. Then, to determine the energetic cost of these activities, she recorded oxygen consumption during activities of seven young otters (in rehabilitation for release back into the wild) at the Monterey Bay Aquarium. Thometz then estimated that moms had to double their energy intake when caring for a large pup. After pregnancy and nursing, females may be too energetically depleted to meet those demands without risking their own lives, she said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Sea otters are apex predators in the kelp forest. If we understand what impacts their population, we’ll understand more about our coastal ecosystems,” Thometz said.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>/2015/sea-otter-supermoms/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2015/sea-otter-supermoms/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Reforming prisons</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Imagine living in a cell barely big enough to hold a king-sized bed, a small sink, and a toilet. But there’s no big bed, only a narrow bunk. There’s no window either, just a fluorescent light that turns on, then off again, each day. The door opens only from the outside and it doesn’t open often. This is solitary confinement, a place where prisoners lose all forms of social contact, sometimes for so many years they never regain the ability to be a friend, or part of a family, again. It’s more akin to torture than reform. And it’s a practice that Craig Haney, a psychology professor at UC Santa Cruz, has studied—and criticized—for more than 20 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The emphasis ought to be on keeping prison isolation as brief and humane as possible and only as a last resort,” Haney said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Haney has interviewed about one thousand prisoners, some of whom have endured solitary confinement for more than two decades. He’s witnessed the anguish, loneliness, and even madness, caused or enforced by isolation. His psychological evaluations are the evidence he takes to courts, legislative committees, and classrooms, to make the case for scaling back the use of solitary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After waging this battle for decades—as a lawyer, an academic and a fellow human—he may be winning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solitary confinement was in vogue in the 1800s. Back then, some believed that a man might atone and make his peace with God if left alone long enough. But by the end of the century that theory was debunked as counterproductive and harmful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the use of long-term prison isolation is rare in the developed world, in the U.S. the penal practice was revived during the 1980s and ’90s when prison populations swelled as a result of tough-on-crime laws and increased mandatory sentencing requirements. At the same time, prison administrators dropped the veneer of prison as a place for rehabilitation, cutting therapeutic and recreational programming, and cementing its function as a tool of punishment. Crowded prisons were dangerous, and overwhelmed administrators began sending some men—whose primary offense might only be a gang-affiliated tattoo—to “the hole” for an indefinite period. Although women prisoners also get solitary confinement, incarcerated men outnumber women by more than a ten-to-one ratio, so the absolute number of women in isolation units is much smaller, Haney noted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/craig-haney-prisons-640.jpg?cb=887f21bf9f2579297c19949ee8fde909&quot; alt=&quot;Craig Haney&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In California, many of these isolated prisoners are held in a “Security Housing Unit” at Pelican Bay State Prison. Located near the Oregon border, the entire facility is devoted to solitary confinement. But throughout the country, an estimated 80,000 prisoners, almost all men, are held in isolation. Some institutions call it “administrative segregation” or “intensive management.” No matter the name, it’s still solitary confinement: a life lived essentially around-the-clock within the same four walls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this so-called “separate world,” one prisoner told Haney: “You get irrationally angry, depression would come in. You had to deal with it every day, fight it off, push it back. You are always on the edge, scared.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some prisoners survive by developing a strict, entirely self-imposed discipline. But no one emerges unscathed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Haney has “mapped the nature of the suffering” for prisoners and the statistics are sobering. In one study he found that more than 91 percent of prisoners in solitary suffer anxiety; 88 percent experience irrational anger, and the same percentage have headaches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He could find no comparably traumatized population in the medical or psychiatric literature—the closest match was a study on former East German psychiatric prisoners, but even they were healthier than the inmates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Haney’s first exposure to the trauma of imprisonment came when he was a student at Stanford, where he earned his law degree and a doctorate in psychology. There, with social psychology maverick Philip Zimbardo, he conducted the famous 1971 Stanford Prison Experiment, a prison simulation that was aborted when the students playing “guards” began abusing the students playing “prisoners.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever since, Haney has focused his studies on improving prison conditions, an emphasis that colleagues say distinguishes him not just as an academic, but also as a force for change. “Haney has become a powerful voice for the disenfranchised, recognized internationally as a leader in the effort to make our prisons into places of rehabilitation, rather than dungeons of dark despair,” said Stuart Grassian, an expert on solitary confinement and a former Harvard Medical School psychiatrist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Haney arrived at UCSC in 1977, he was already immersed in examining the backgrounds of prisoners on death row and others accused of capital crimes. His efforts uncovered dramatic similarities in their backgrounds: Many of these inmates had suffered severe poverty, abuse or neglect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also studied the way the death penalty was implemented and imposed in the United States. “The system of capital punishment operates in a way dramatically at odds with the way the public thinks it does,” Haney said. “It is nowhere near as rational, nowhere near as fair, and nowhere near as effective.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His early research showed, for example, that asking a potential juror—in front of others—if they’d be willing to impose the death penalty biased the juror pool. It eliminated death penalty opponents from participating and suggested to the jurors that perhaps the death penalty was the correct sentence, Haney said. In 2005, he published many of the lessons gleaned from such studies in an award-winning book, Death by Design. His research contributed to changes in the way the system operated, from jury selection to jury instructions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As his work progressed, Haney spent more and more time investigating the effects of the increasing use of solitary confinement, although he still considers his main focus to be on the effects of imprisonment in general. “It became the tail that wags the dog,” he said. He testified in the 1995 case Madrid v. Gomez, in which U.S. Chief Judge Thelton Henderson ruled solitary confinement violated the rights of the mentally ill with an oft-quoted statement: 23 hours in isolation “may press the outer borders of what most humans can psychologically tolerate.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Haney was also one of the “critical forces” behind Brown v. Plata, the 2011 U.S. Supreme Court case that ruled overcrowding violated prisoners’ constitutional rights, said Mona Lynch, a UC Irvine professor of criminology who earned her doctoral degree as Haney’s student in 1997. “He was key to making the link between the conditions in the prison and what that did to people and how it rose to the level of being unconstitutional.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That work is slowly beginning to pay off. The prison population in California has declined following the Supreme Court’s order. In addition, many politicians and prison administrators across the country are beginning to understand that solitary confinement isn’t the best way to address prison conflict and disruptive behavior, Haney said. From a financial standpoint, isolation is expensive. For administrators facing budget cuts, it’s hard to fund the extra staff required to hand-deliver meals and escort prisoners to exercise. Moreover, public awareness—and disapproval—is growing, leading some states to cut back its use. For example, in Mississippi and Washington the number of isolated prisoners has been slashed, and Maine reduced its numbers by 70 percent in just four years. In New York and Colorado, isolation is no longer used for the mentally ill. And, just this year, New York City declared an end to solitary confinement for prisoners younger than 21 years of age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be clear, Haney recognizes the occasional need to separate prisoners, sometimes for their own safety. But their time alone should be short and free from unnecessary deprivations, he said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When not in court, visiting prisons, or teaching courses on psychology and law, Haney can often be found in his corner office in College Ten, a well-lived-in space with family photos and 15-foot-long bookshelves. Haney has no plans to leave, or retire, anytime soon. “Santa Cruz has been an absolutely ideal intellectual environment for me,” Haney said. 
His career has been a success by any standards. The recipient of numerous awards, Haney is considered “a leader and a superstar in the field,” said Keramet Reiter, a UC Irvine assistant professor, herself an expert on solitary confinement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Haney isn’t resting on his laurels. He’s writing a book on solitary confinement and contributing to a project funded by a UC President’s Research Catalyst Award to improve prisoner medical and mental health care. In addition, he’s organizing an effort to spur criminal justice reform using evidence-based methods, an undertaking that Haney hopes to base at UC Santa Cruz. He also just returned from the Bipartisan Summit on Criminal Justice Reform, where the urgent need for substantial criminal justice reform dominated the agenda.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>/2015/reforming-prisons/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2015/reforming-prisons/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Reclassifying Cancer</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Cancers are often categorized–and treated–according to where they are found in the body. But it may be more effective to base treatment on the molecular makeup of cancers, regardless of where they occur, according to a study published in Cell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same role can be played by cells in different parts of the body, explained Josh Stuart, a professor of biomolecular engineering at UC Santa Cruz and senior author on the paper. For example, cells that develop to form layers on surfaces may line the bladder, the throat, or other places. With similar origins, these cells may also share molecular pathways leading to cancer, and respond to the same treatments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the TCGA Pan-Cancer Initiative, a team from UCSC and the Buck Institute for Research on Aging led researchers to analyze data from 3,500 patients with 12 different cancer types. When the cancers were grouped by “cell of origin,” the data suggested that 10 percent of these cancers could be reclassified, potentially leading to different treatment options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This molecular information gives us a new kind of microscope to look at cancer,” said Stuart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The researchers are now refining their results, analyzing 35 tumor types from 11,000 patient samples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UCSC-Buck team is led by Josh Stuart, David Haussler, the director of the UCSC Genomics Institute, and Christopher Benz, of the Buck Institute in California.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>/2015/reclassifying-cancer/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2015/reclassifying-cancer/</guid>
        
        
        <category>biomolecular engineering</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Property and Power</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The global rise of violence against women reflects inequalities in the structure of societies. In developing countries, where property confers power, women who own land are less likely to be victims of abuse, according to a study published in Psychology of Women Quarterly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Violence against women doesn’t start as an abusive relationship,” said Shelly Grabe, an associate professor of psychology at UC Santa Cruz who led the research. “The abuses of power start at a much higher level. If we want to eradicate abuse, we need to go back to those larger structural relationships. Of those larger relationships, land ownership is key.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grabe interviewed 492 women in Nicaragua and Tanzania. She gathered information that included their age, education, number of children, experience of violence, and land ownership. Her analysis suggested that shifting control over resources–land in particular\0xAD\0xAD–can dramatically change women’s lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One interviewee said: “Those times he used to beat you, he beats you because he knows you depend on him…But if he finds you have your own place, he can’t be able.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“My data documents that we need to challenge the roots of abuse, rather than dealing with con-sequences,” said Grabe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rose Grace Grose and Anjali Dutt, graduate students in psychology, were co-authors on this study.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>/2015/property-and-power/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2015/property-and-power/</guid>
        
        
        <category>psychology</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>People make pumas eat and run</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Pumas don’t like hanging around human dwellings. That’s good news for people. But that aversion makes the big cats kill more often when they live near high-density housing, according to a study published in the Proceedings of the Royal Society B. That behavior may affect local prey populations and the reproductive success of the pumas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a kill, mountain lions usually spend several days close to the carcass, eating their fill, explained Justine Smith, a Ph.D. candidate in the UC Santa Cruz Environmental Studies Department, and lead author on the study. “When humans are around, the animals leave their kill more often. That’s a lot of time and energy to give up, especially for females raising cubs,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The researchers followed 30 pumas that were outfitted with GPS monitoring collars, as part of the Santa Cruz Puma Project, led by Christopher Wilmers, associate professor of environmental studies. They found that females living in the highest housing density areas killed 36 percent more deer each year than females in more pristine habitats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We might be optimistic about results that show pumas can hunt successfully in a developed landscape,” said Smith. “But we know it takes substantial energy to hunt, and some of these females are killing a lot more.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a previous study, led by Terrie Williams, UCSC professor of ecology and evolutionary biology, researchers calculated the caloric cost of various hunting strategies–waiting, stalking, or pouncing. The results, published in Science, showed pumas save their high-calorie burning efforts for the bigger prey payoffs.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>/2015/people-and-pumas/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2015/people-and-pumas/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Connected Community</title>
        <description>&lt;h2&gt;Vote Local&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among countries where citizens can vote, the United States holds one of the lowest voter turnout records. Ironically, when states restrict voting rights, those efforts are always more effective than campaigns designed to bring more voters to the ballot box. However, the same state laws that help create low turnouts may offer insights for reform, said Melanie Jean Springer, an assistant professor of politics at UCSC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In her book, How the States Shaped the Nation: American Electoral Institutions and Voter Turnout 1920–2000, Springer analyzed 80 years of voting history. Her research showed that each state has considerable influence on local voting culture. For instance, some states require that voters have particular kinds of photo identification, which may be too costly for some citizens to obtain. Paying attention to those state-specific effects is the ticket to building more participation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We need to look at the history of how states encourage or discourage voting,“ Springer said, “and then be more mindful about how we aim to engage people.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Green Dreams&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early on, the organic farming movement found wide appeal among California’s back-to-nature crowd. But it wasn’t long before this “weird hippie interest” became a selling feature in high-end restaurants, said Julie Guthman, a UC Santa Cruz professor of social sciences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the second edition of Agrarian Dreams: The Paradox of Organic Farming in California, Guthman takes another look at the influence of agribusiness and foodie sensibilities on the organic food movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There’s all this attention on organics, yet only one percent of U.S. farmland grows organic food,” said Guthman. “This is because the market still turns on a voluntary system of regulations and consumers’ willingness to pay more.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The high cost of land puts growers under great pressure to get more crop value per acre. So, the system ends up being very similar to conventional agribusiness models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s a California story, but the implications are much wider,” said Guthman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Jazz Fusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s been fourteen years since Eric Porter and Lewis Watts met as new professors at UC Santa Cruz. With a mutual passion for jazz history, their collaboration was only a matter of time. Involving New Orleans, the birthplace of jazz, was inevitable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Hurricane Katrina stormed through the city, wreaking cultural transformation in its wake, the men found the story they wanted to tell: Porter with prose, Watts with images. Their book, New Orleans Suite: Music and Culture in Transition, was published by UC Press in 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We wanted to showcase the role that cultural practices play in everyday lives in New Orleans, and also the way these practices were mobilized to rebuild the city,” said Porter, a professor in the History and History of Consciousness Departments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In black-and-white photography, Watts, a professor emeritus of arts, reveals the place and its people before and after the hurricane hit. “We managed to meld words and images to approach the city through its music,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Carrying On&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the early 1990s, New Queer Cinema emerged as an amalgam of art and activism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The movement was fueled by a potent combination of politics, AIDS, camcorders, and cheap rent, said B. Ruby Rich, author of New Queer Cinema: The Director’s Cut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“When I started formulating these ideas, the AIDS epidemic was still new,” said Rich, a professor in the Social Documentation Program and the Film and Digital Media Department. “There was an enormous amount of panic, grief and shock in the community. New Queer Cinema represented a second phase, a time to gather strength and try to express something other than mourning. I coined the name as a way to try to clear a space for this.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this book, Rich brings back her early essays about the rise of gay and lesbian cinematic themes, and updates her writing with new testaments to LGBT influences on film and life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rich is also the editor of Film Quarterly, the film journal of the University of California Press.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Looking for Law&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The politically unstable setting of Sudan might appear an unlikely place to investigate the power of law. But it seemed ideal to Mark Fathi Massoud, an assistant professor of politics and legal studies at UC Santa Cruz.
Sudan was the first sub-Saharan African country to achieve colonial independence from the British. Its post-independence period has been wracked by warfare, slaughter, and instability. Massoud’s family fled from there in 1983, when war resumed after a decade of relative calm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I hoped to learn more about my homeland and the people who had stayed behind, and also to make sense of how law matters and fails to matter in the most unexpected places,” Massoud said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The culmination of Massoud’s research, Law’s Fragile State: Colonial, Authoritarian and Humanitarian Legacies in Sudan,  was published by Cambridge University Press in 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His book received the 2014 Law and Society Association’s Herbert Jacob Prize for the best book in law and society published in the previous year.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>/2015/pen-and-inq/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2015/pen-and-inq/</guid>
        
        
        <category>information technology</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Outsider insights</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Dynasties of war, revolution, and imperial rule fill the records of China’s past. Historians, both in this country and abroad, examine how the legacy of these events influenced subsequent culture. Scholars based in China tend to view that history through its relationship with their own traditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the three China historians at UC Santa Cruz are all outsiders to the culture. Through unique blends of scholarship and collaboration, they connect ideas from other social sciences and branches of history to big events in Chinese history. These cross-cultural perspectives help them reveal history that is often more complex than it first appears, and their collaborations continue to create new opportunities for research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For these UCSC historians, outside perspective comes from their own life experiences, as well as conversations and collaborations with scholars from other fields.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Displaced youth&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1979, Emily Honig spent two years in Shanghai, working on her dissertation research at Fudan University and studying the lives of women workers in the city. “I was interested in social networks and where people came from and how that impacted their experience,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, Honig is a professor of history at UCSC, and she’s working on a project conceived during those dissertation days. Her book-in-progress explores the “sent-down youth” movement, a program that Communist leaders envisioned as a way to “re-educate” urban youth in the traditional ways of life. Not coincidentally, her collaborator is Xiaojian Zhao, a former next-door neighbor from the Fudan student dormitories. Now a professor of Asian-American history at UC Santa Barbara, Zhao was one of the millions of urban teenagers sent to live with peasants in the countryside during the 1960s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About five years ago, the women traveled to the rural village where Zhao lived during her teenage years. The two visited the county’s archive, and archives from other areas that hosted urban youth. There they found a wealth of information that hadn’t been described in any other books or journals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, some records revealed unexpected associations. Honig said she and Zhao kept finding lists of items like tires, tractors, electrical wire, broadcast cable, and high-pressure water pumps. At first, the researchers ignored these records, thinking they were irrelevant to their questions. But the sheer abundance of these lists forced the researchers to take a closer look. The women then realized that the county offices of the “sent-down youth” movement were requesting material goods from the city offices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There was this whole behind-the-scenes economic exchange between major industrial cities like Shanghai and Beijing and remote areas, even though state policy basically said that local villages can’t acquire equipment from anywhere,” Honig said. “But because of the ‘sent-down youth’ movement, unbelievable amounts of material goods were sent to the countryside.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She thinks it was a way for Shanghai families to send goods to the towns where their children were living, hopefully enabling the villages to establish factories where the kids could work instead of the fields. Stories of riding tractors or transporting equipment from the cities could seem too mundane to arise during interviews or in memoirs. But once asked about it, people who were transplanted during their youth can tell plenty of stories about equipment, Honig said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The collaboration with Honig is useful, said Zhao, because they each bring different scholarly and personal perspectives to the topic. She and Honig have presented their work at international conferences, and Zhao said their book is already anticipated by Chinese-speaking scholars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Rural voices&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working with someone closely connected to an issue was also critical for Gail Hershatter, a distinguished professor of history at UCSC and member of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, when she researched her most recent book. Published in 2011, The Gender of Memory: Rural Women in China’s Collective Past, presents rural women’s perspectives about their lives during the country’s transition to socialism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hershatter gathered material for her book with Gao Xiaoxian, a researcher involved with rural development projects in her home province of Shaanxi, about 900 miles west-northwest of Shanghai. The two women met at a conference in 1992, and they shared an interest in learning about the life in the countryside during the revolution. Hershatter feels that her collaborator was essential to the research process. Gao Xiaoxian worked in the countryside and was already accepted by many villagers. That meant it took less time for the women to accept Hershatter into their community and feel comfortable enough to share personal stories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Hershatter inquired about rural life, she discovered the written and oral record of the countryside was bursting with stories that people were eager to tell, yet no one had asked about. Even today, research in the countryside is challenging; the area is large and there is little infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From 1996 to 2006, Hershatter and Gao interviewed 72 women, and a few men, from villages in central and southern Shaanxi province. Rural women were not shy about complaining about their lives. Once you asked, Hershatter said, “you’d better have four or five hours because all these pent up stories would come pouring out.” The women talked of the physical labor of working in the fields, travails of raising children, the constant work of sewing clothes, and attending party meetings in the village.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two collaborators also searched regional archives, looking for materials that revealed govern-mental goals for building socialism. These materials also reported problems that occurred while ending arranged marriages, reorganizing ownership of farm fields, and increasing agricultural production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the state’s perspective, the new policies created a new era of freedom for women. But from the women’s perspective, socialism did little to ease daily hardships. Men left the villages for paid work nearby. Women took over the agricultural duties, working in the fields during the day to maximize grain production. At night, they also cooked, cared for the children, and sewed clothes and shoes. Some women reported basically not sleeping for years.&lt;br /&gt;
“If you look at the state trying to do this big modernization project by drawing on peasant labor, women are the center of it because their paid and their unpaid [domestic] labor is underwriting the whole project,” Hershatter said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reviewers of her book noted that it provides the first personal accounts of major government campaigns of the 1950s. “[T]his is one of the rare books that transform our understanding of the Chinese revolution and, at the same time, makes us think about the way we practice history,” wrote Jacob Eyferth, an East Asian historian at the University of Chicago, in the May 2014 issue of The PRC History Review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hershatter expects more scholarship about rural China and the revolution to emerge in the future. Since starting this project, she’s noticed that graduate students in history programs at some Chinese universities are being encouraged to interview their aging grandparents before their stories are lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Intellectual evolution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes perspectives disappear over centuries of cultural change. Dai Zhen was an influential 18th-century Chinese intellectual who assimilated European knowledge of mathematics and astronomy into Chinese culture. Dai also challenged the imperial hierarchy with talk of individualism. His cultural influence wavered during the end of the 18th century and the beginning of the 19th century. But in the 20th century, Dai reappeared as a revered figure. Some of his humanitarian and individualistic philosophy was used as a slogan during the Cultural Revolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, historians studying the impact of Dai’s work tend to focus either on his scientific knowledge or his philosophical legacy. Minghui Hu, an associate professor of history at UCSC, wanted to investigate Dai as both a scientist and philosopher, and then follow the way both aspects of Dai’s ideas percolated through Chinese culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his new book, Hu recounts how Dai absorbed the latest astronomical knowledge from Jesuit missionaries who arrived in China during the 17th century. That knowledge also fueled Dai’s social criticism and philosophical legacy. Hu’s book, China’s Transition to Modernity: The New Classical Vision of Dai Zhen, will be published in June. “As a historian, I wrote this book intending to restore what [Dai] was doing back to its time,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though he grew up in Taiwan and memorized classical Chinese texts during school, Hu considers himself an outsider to Chinese culture. He came to the United States at the age of 25, to attend graduate school in science and technology studies, a field that uses history, sociology, and philosophy to examine the intersection of science and culture. He went on to obtain his doctorate in the history of science, and Hu’s adviser recommended that he combine his science background with his ability to read classical Chinese texts to study the history of Chinese science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hu notes that a trio of China historians in one department is rare at universities today, and that concentration of scholars bolsters the impact of their research. All three—Hershatter, Honig, and Hu—have collaborated with scholars in, or from, China. They also incorporate theories from the humanities and social sciences into their historical inquiries. That depth and breadth of experience has attracted graduate students from all over the world, many of whom are now professors at other universities and colleges. Of their efforts, Hu said: “We are trying to become a major center of China history in the UC system, and in the country.”&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>/2015/outsider-insights/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2015/outsider-insights/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Leading research influence</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;UC Santa Cruz ranked first in research influence
among the world’s top universities, according to the World University Rankings, published annually by Times Higher Education (THE).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This placing should come as no surprise to anyone familiar with UCSC,” said Scott Brandt, vice chancellor for research. “That is an accurate reflection of the world-class research that takes place across our campus. UCSC is too small to be best at everything, but it is big enough to be best at everything we choose to do. That is as true of our research–as reflected in THE rankings–as it is of the educational opportunities that we provide to our students.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slugs earned the top slot with a citation score of 100, tying for first place with MIT, and edging out Rice University at 99.9. The score is based on counting the average number of times publications by UCSC researchers were cited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The spirit of inquiry@UC Santa Cruz&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the inaugural issue of inquiry@UC Santa Cruz. The office of Research and University Relations are proud to sponsor this annual research magazine. The purpose of inquiry is to present a campus-wide snapshot of our world-class research and a sense of “who we are” as a community of researchers and to draw out the complex interplay between pioneering research at
UCSC and our investigators’ vision and passion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reading through these briefs and features, one finds the diversity of high-impact research at UCSC striking. We see examples of UC researchers conducting and leading complex inter-institutional scientific research to better understand our changing natural world; we see humanist archival scholarship retrieving worlds of lost cultural meaning; we see monographs
on prison reform that are informing policy decisions; and we see the development of new technologies to aid and empower people with physical challenges. No wonder the Times Higher Education World University Rankings placed UCSC #1 in the world in research impact and #8 overall among world universities under 50 years old!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hope you enjoy inquiry@UC Santa Cruz for 2015–16. It is a great privilege to support and foster the growth of research at UC Santa Cruz as we celebrate our 50th anniversary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scott A. Brandt&lt;br /&gt;
Vice Chancellor for Research&lt;br /&gt;
and Professor of Computer Science&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Credits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;University Of California Santa Cruz&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chancellor: George Blumenthal&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Campus Provost and Executive Vice Chancellor: Alison Galloway&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vice Chancellor, Research: Scott Brandt&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vice Chancellor, University Relations: Keith Brant&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;inquiry@UC Santa Cruz&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;2015–16&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Editor: Elizabeth Devitt&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Creative Director: Lisa Nielsen&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Art Director/Designer: Linda Knudson (Cowell ’76)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Associate Editors
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Quentin Williams&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Principal Jeanne Lance&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Tedd Siegel&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Lynne Stoops&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Photography
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Carolyn Lagattuta&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Elena Zhukova&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Contributors
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Anil Ananthaswamy (SciCom ’00)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Becky Bach (SciCom ’14)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Elizabeth Devitt (SciCom ’13)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Jennie Dusheck (SciCom ’85)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Melissae Fellet (SciCom ’11)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Heather Rock Woods (SciCom ’94)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Helen Shen (SciCom ’12)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Danielle Venton (SciCom ’11)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Image Research
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Linda Knudson&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Produced by UC Santa Cruz Communications &amp;amp; Marketing&lt;br /&gt;
1156 High Street
Santa Cruz, CA 95064-1077&lt;br /&gt;
E-mail: inquiry@ucsc.edu&lt;br /&gt;
Web: research.ucsc.edu &amp;amp; www.ucsc.edu&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>/2015/opener/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2015/opener/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
